Guide to the John William Gardner Papers, 1961-1992
Department of Special Collections
Gardner, John William, 1912 -. Papers,
1961-1992
M0659
Gardner, John William, 1912-
7 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of John William Gardner, 1992 and 1993.
Biography
Served as Secretary of Health, Education, and Welfare from 1965 to 1968, and subsequently became chairman of the National Urban Coalition. He founded the organizations Common Cause and Independent Sector. He is the author of several books on education and leadership. In 1964, Professor Gardner was awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom. He is currently a professor in the Graduate School of Business at Stanford University.
Scope and Content
The papers include original manuscripts and notes of many publications, 1961-1975, as well as files from the major task forces and commissions on which Gardner served, 1962-1982. There is considerable material from the National Urban Coalition including correspondence with national statesmen and political and economic leaders, board meeting files, reports and publications, 1968-1970.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
National Urban Coalition.; United States. President's Commission for a National Agenda for.; United States. President's Task Force on Private Sector.; United States. White House Task Force on Education.; United States. White House Conference on Education.; United States. Commission on International Education and.; Education.; Excellence in a free society.; The Godkin lectures.; In common cause.; Know or listen to those who know.; No easy victories.; Recovery of confidence.; Self-renewal.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Files from major task forces and commissions
  - President Kennedy's Commission on International Educational and Cultural Exchange, 1962 - 1965 (Box 1)
  - President Johnson's White House Conference on Education, 1964 - 1965 (Box 1)
  - United States. President Commission for a National Agenda for the Eighties, 1979 - 1980 (Box 1)
  - United States. President's Task Force on Private Sector Initiatives, 1962 - 1965 (Box 2)
  - White House Task Force on Education, 1964 (Box 2)
  - White House Task Force on Education, 1964 (Box 3)
  - White House Task Force on Education, 1964 (Box 4)
- Series 2. Manuscripts, corrected typescripts, and galleys of published works
  - The Godkin lectures, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Recovery of confidence, ca. 1970 (Box 5)
  - Excellence in a free society, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Self-renewal, 1963 (Box 7)
  - No easy victories, 1968 (Box 7)
  - Know or listen to those who know, 1975 (Box 7)
  - In common cause, 1972 (Box 8)
- Series 3. National Urban Coalition
  - Beginnings, board meetings, 1968 - 1970, and press releases and memos, 1968 (Box 9)
  - Press releases and memos, 1969 - 1970, published reports (Box 10)
  - Testimony of Otto Kerner on violence, 1967 (Box 11)
  - Itineraries, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Urban America, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Reuben Salazar, n.d. (Box 11)
  - William A. Slayton, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Dickie S. Carter, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Gustav Heningburg, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Later (1970s and 1980s) correspondence and report, ca. 1970 - 1989 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, A - B, 1968 - 1969 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, C - D, 1968 - 1969 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, E - F, 1968 - 1969 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, H, 1968 - 1969 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, H, 1968 - 1969 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, J, 1968 - 1969 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, K, 1968 - 1969 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, L, 1968 - 1969 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, M, 1968 - 1969 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, N - P, 1968 - 1969 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, R, 1968 - 1969 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, S - T, 1968 - 1969 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, U - Z, 1968 - 1969 (Box 13)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, 1968 (Box 13)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, 1968 (Box 13)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, 1968 (Box 13)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, 1969 - 1970 (Box 13)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, 1969 - 1970 (Box 13)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, 1969 - 1970 (Box 14)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, Correspondence, A - B, 1969 - 1970 (Box 14)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, Correspondence, C - D1969 - 1970 (Box 14)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, Correspondence, E - J1969 - 1970 (Box 14)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, Correspondence, K - M1969 - 1970 (Box 14)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, Correspondence, Q - Z1969 - 1970 (Box 14)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, Fundraising, n.d. (Box 14)
  - Urban Coalition Action Council, Dinners, lunches, n.d. (Box 14)